Hey, my name is Milan, and in this video we're going to explore an interesting messaging library called Wolverine
You may have already heard about it, might have never talked about it on my channel, and we're going to explore it in this video
I wanted to talk about Wolverine for several reasons
First, because it's a very interesting and powerful messaging library
It's part of the broader creator stack
We have another popular library called Martin, which I did talk about in a video a few years ago
It allows you to treat postgress as a document database, and it also gives you support for event sourcing
But let's go back to bullring, it became significantly more popular with mass transit going commercial as people were exploring other options, and I have to say
That I haven't used Wolverine, so you're basically going to see my raw take as a beginner with this library
And I think this perspective might be interesting to some of you
Let me walk you through what I plan to build with Wolverine
I'm basically going
To step through, they're getting started example with just my own messages and handlers, and it's going to be a demo of using wolverine as a command bus
And right now, all of this is going to work in memory
What I already prepared behind the scenes
IS A SIMPLE ASPIRE APPLICATION WITH A WEB API
A POSTGRES DATABASE AND I CONFIGURED IF CORE AND SET UP MY DATABASE MIGRATIONS SO WHAT WE NEED TO DO TO GET STARTED WITH WOLVERINE IS INSTALL THE NEW GET PACKAGE I'M GOING TO LOOK FOR WOLVERINE
And I'm going to install the latest version of Wolverine FX, so let's install that
and then how you add it to your application is you go back to your program file and you can say builder and then host
AND NOW YOU HAVE A NEW EXTENSION METHOD CALLED USE WOLVERINE
SO THIS IS ALL THAT'S REQUIRED FOR THE BASIC SETUP
OF COURSE YOU CAN CUSTOMIZE THIS AS WOLVERINE SUPPORTS
Quite a bit of rich functionality among them support for many popular message transports including rabbit and mq
Azure service bus and SQS
Now I'm going to talk about those in a future video, but now let's keep the wolverine setup as simple as this
So then the next thing we need
There's a command and a respective handler, so this is going to be very similar to something that you're probably used to from Mediator, and I'm going to create a folder called Features, and inside of it I'll define a new folder for my new feature
and let's say i just call this the register feature for lack of a better name
now let me add a new class inside
And this is going to be my first message
So in this case, I am defining a command, and I am going to call this register user
So let's make it a record, and I am going to define a couple of properties that I am going to need for my new user, and it is just going to be an email, a first name
AND A LAST NAME, SO KEEPING IT SIMPLE, AND THIS REPRESENTS OUR MESSAGE CONTRACT
IT DOESN'T MATTER IF YOU'RE USING THIS IN MEMORY OR WITH A MESSAGE TRANSPORT
This is all it takes to define a message
You don't need any specific interface
You'll see that most things with Wolverine work by convention
Now, some people may treat this as a dose of too much magic going on
I certainly need one of those
A bit more strict approach with more rules and abstractions, but I'm open to exploring something different
So let's continue using the default approach, and how we define a handler is we just name a class
WITH THE NAME OF OUR MESSAGE, AND THEN EXTEND THAT WITH HANDLER
NOW YOU CAN USE DEPENDENCY INJECTION IN THIS CLASS AND EVEN USE PRIMARY CONSTRUCTORS FOR THIS
SO LET ME INJECT AN APPLICATION DATABASE CONTEXT AND THIS IS GOING TO WORK, AND THEN TO DEFINE MY ACTUAL HANDLER LOGIC, I JUST NEED TO CREATE
A method called handle the first argument needs to be the message type, so this is going to be register user and let's call this the command and I'm going to accept this completion from visual studio
CREATING A NEW USER AND SETTING THE RESPECTIVE PROPERTIES, AND ADDITIONALLY I'M GOING TO DEFINE THE CREATED AD FIELD AND LET'S JUST SET THIS TO DATE TIME UTC NOW SINCE THE IDENTIFIER IS GOOD
I'm going to say go with new good and create that, and this gives us our first entity
So you can see I don't need to have any abstractions here, although there is a way to achieve this
You can implement an interface that exposes a handle method
OR YOU CAN DECORATE YOUR TYPE WITH AN ATTRIBUTE
NOW LET'S CONTINUE USING THE CONVENTIONAL APPROACH, AND WE HAVE OUR HANDLER AND A MESSAGE, AND NOW ALL WE NEED TO DO IS EXPOSE AN API ENDPOINT THAT WE CAN CALL SAUCY APP MAP
POST I'LL USE MINIMAL APIS LET'S SAY THE ROUTE IS JUST USERS AND THE REQUEST ARGUMENT IS GOING TO BE THE REGISTER USER COMMAND I'LL CALL IT A COMMAND AND THEN HERE'S HOW YOU INTERACT WITH WOLVERINE THERE'S AN INTERFACE CALLED I MESSAGE BUS AND
This allows you to call the respective methods that are available
One of those is invoke async
Where we can just pass our command, and this is going to hand off the execution to the Wolverine pipeline is going to find and execute our handler, and then we're going to return the response from our API endpoint
So let's go ahead and test this out
I'm going to start this application
You'll see
See the Aspire dashboard and application getting started and I'm going to open up the scaler UI that contains my endpoint
HERE'S THE ONE ENDPOINT THAT I HAVE
I'M GOING TO GO AHEAD AND TEST IT OUT
And let's give this dummy email, let's say test at test
com, and the first name and last name I'm going to have the same values, and I'm going to send this request
And you can see that we had a breakpoint in our minimal API endpoint, and if I hit continue, this will be handed off to Wolverine
IS GOING TO INVOKE MY REGISTER USER HANDLER
NOTICE THAT THE DATABASE CONTEXT IS PROPERLY INJECTED FROM DEPENDENCY INJECTION
I CAN GO AHEAD AND CREATE MY USER AND PERSIST THIS TO MY POSTGRES DATABASE
AND IF I HIT CONTINUE, I'LL GET A TWO HUNDRED OK RESPONSE BACK IN SCALAR
IF WE TAKE A LOOK AT C DISTRIBUTED TRACES
YOU CAN SEE WE HAVE TWO SPANS IN THE STRAYS, OUR API CALL AND OUR SQL QUERY TO INSERT THE USER
YOU CAN SEE IT TAKES A VERY MINIMAL AMOUNT OF CODE TO CREATE A FUNCTIONAL MESSAGING APPLICATION
SO WHAT CAN WE DO NEXT FROM HERE?
WELL, WOOVERING HAS THIS CONCEPT
Except
Of cascading messages, so let me go ahead and add a new class
So let's say after we've created a user, we also want to publish an event
THIS EVENT IS GOING TO BE CALLED USER REGISTERED
LET'S ALSO MAKE IT A RECORD, AND I'M JUST GOING TO GIVE IT THE USER ID AS THE ONLY ARGUMENT
NOW HOW YOU WOULD TYPICALLY PUBLISH THIS
WITH SOME OTHER LIBRARIES, AS LET'S SAY MEDIATOR HAS THIS NOTIFICATION APPROACH, YOU WOULD NEED ACCESS TO THE I MEDIATOR OR I PUBLISHER INSTANCES, AND THEN MANUALLY CALL THE PUBLISHMENT WITH WOLVERINE
What you can do is return an object or a message from this handle method, and in this case this will be user registered
With the respective value, now I do have to update the signature here to also return the same type, and now this will be treated as a cascading message
AND MOBILRING IS GOING TO PUBLISH IT AFTER THIS ONE COMPLETES
NOW FOR THIS MESSAGE, I CAN ALSO CREATE A RESPECTIVE HAMMER, AND THE CONVENTION IS THE SAME AS BEFORE
YOU USE THE MESSAGE NAME, SO LET'S SAY USER REGISTER
And we append handler
What's interesting is that this class can even be static, doesn't have to be a typical class, and inside of it I can define a static handle method
So let's say public static, async task, handle
WE HAVE TO ACCEPT OUR MESSAGE, SO LET'S SAY EVENT, AND THEN I'M GOING TO SAY AWAIT, TASK, DELAY, AND FOR EXAMPLE DELAY FOR A SECOND TO SIMULATE SOME MESSAGE PROCESSING
So let's place a breakpoint here, and let's run the application again
And from the scaler UI, I will go ahead and send my test request
We again had our breakpoint inside of our minimal API endpoint, where I will press continue
THE NEXT BREAK WHEN WE HIT IS INSIDE OUR HANDLE METHOD, WHERE WE GO THROUGH THE REGULAR FLOW, OPERATING AN ENTITY, ADDING IT TO OUR DATABASE CONTEXT, AND THEN PERSISTING EVERYTHING AFTER CALLING SAFE CHANGES
SO THIS COMPLETES OUR NORMAL FLOW
AND NOW WE WANT TO PUBLISH THIS USER REGISTER EVENT, SO IF I KEEP GOING AFTER THIS LINE, YOU'LL SEE THAT WE NOW HAD THE BREAK POINT
In the user registered handler, and if we take a look at the object that we got
It contains the identifier of our newly created user
So now we could do something like set up their account, maybe create a new tenant for them or just send them a welcome email
The options are limitless, but I wanted to highlight how easy it is
To start building non-trivial messaging applications with Wolverine
Now, this isn't a sponsored video
I'm just a newbie exploring Wolverine, the same as some of you out there, and so far I like it
Now, what I want to see next is how it integrates with
my favorite message transport which is rabbitmq
How it deals with the message topology, with the bindings and exchanges and cues
That's a topic for another video
One more thing I wanted to highlight about Wolverine is that they have amazing documentation
It's full of examples
It contains
Everything you probably need to get started with using it, and they also have a nice community of folks who like using these libraries
So I'm going to drop the link to this in the description of this video where you can learn more, and then stay tuned for more videos about Wolverine where we're going to
Lord some advanced topics, what we covered so far works only in memory, so it's fairly limited for a serious production system
But if you want to learn how to use RabbitMQ to build a messaging application
Go ahead and watch this video next
Let me know in the comments what you think about Wolverine
Smash the like button for the YouTube algorithm so this gets recommended to more data developers
Thanks a lot for watching and until next time stay
AWESOME